<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: d3 | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/d3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-23T15:40:36-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seattle Restaurant Changes]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/04/17/seattle-restaurant-changes/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-17T10:51:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/04/17/seattle-restaurant-changes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Seattle construction is currently booming and I was interested in how
that
reflected in the local restaurant scene. There are many food blogs and
local news sites that cover openings and closings, but I found it too
difficult to parse these in a regular manner. Fortunately I was able to
use data from the <a href="http://www.seattle.gov/licenses/find-a-business">City of Seattle business
finder</a> and used the
restaurant classification or
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NAICS">NAICS</a> code as a proxy. Using the
data in this manner makes an assumption that a restaurant will no longer
have a business licence after it closes.
I&rsquo;m not sure how accurate this is but I figured it was as accurate as I
could get short of hiring people on Mechanical Turk to phone every
restaurant every week and ask if the restaurant is still open. To map each
restaurant to a particular neighborhood, I
used geolocation to map license address returned by the City of Seattle business
finder. Obviously that does not work as well for Mobile Food Services
(i.e. food trucks) but it still allows for an interesting comparison.
This data is plotted at <a href="http://seattlerestaurantchanges.com">Seattle Restaurant
Changes</a>.</p>

<p>I initially attempted to scrape
data from <a href="https://www.thestranger.com/food-and-drink">The Stranger</a> but
after finding the City of Seattle site I just used
<a href="http://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">BeautifulSoup</a> for the
scraping. I would not have been able to do much more beyond that state
if it had not been for Nathan Yau&rsquo;s excellent tutorial on <a href="http://flowingdata.com/2015/02/19/make-an-interactive-map-with-category-filters/">making maps
with category
filters</a>.
I was able to get a state level shapefile for Washington state from
<a href="http://www.zillow.com/blog/7000-neighborhood-boundary-files-in-shapefile-format-4653/">Zillow</a>
and then reduce that to just Seattle neighborhoods using R&rsquo;s
<a href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sp/">sp</a> package. Full code
posted on <a href="https://github.com/stedy/seattle-restaurants">github</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
