<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gis,r,topojson | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/gis-r-topojson/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-08-28T11:23:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping Seattle Traffic Circles]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/09/21/mapping-seattle-traffic-circles/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-21T22:03:39-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/09/21/mapping-seattle-traffic-circles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, there was a post on Priceonomics about traffic circles with
the argument that roundabouts are <a href="http://priceonomics.com/the-case-for-more-traffic-roundabouts/">safer, help improve traffic flow, and
reduce emissions</a>.
The post mentions that there are 3700 roundabouts in the United States,
which made me wonder - how many of those are in Seattle?</p>

<p>Fortunately, the <a href="https://data.seattle.gov/">City of Seattle data site</a>
has GIS data for all streets as well as GIS data for all traffic
circles. The traffic circles dataset had 1042 total entries or about a
third of the total number of roundabouts in the United States. I&rsquo;m not
sure how accurate that is but I think focusing on traffic circles within
the city limits is more interesting.</p>

<p>I used the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sp/">sp library</a> in
R to read in both sets of shapefiles and quickly determine the streets
with the highest number of roundabouts:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> street </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> count </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> FREMONT AVE N </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1ST AVE NW </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 8TH AVE NE </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> DAYTON AVE N </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 6TH AVE NW </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 12TH AVE NE </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Fremont Ave N. has a whopping 27 traffic circles which seems excessive
until you realize that most of these are North of the zoo and not in the
denser southern part of the street.</p>

<p>I thought quite a bit about how to best represent these values and
ultimately
settled on mapping streets colored to the number of traffic
circles on that street. I used R and <a href="http://colorbrewer2.org/">Color Brewer</a> to make a color attribute for the map based on traffic circle count that could be read by Leaflet. I wrote out my GeoJSON files using
<code>rgdal::writeOGR()</code> and then found that was way too slow to reasonably
run in a browser so I converted it to
<a href="https://github.com/mbostock/topojson">topojson</a> using <code>topojson -o colored_traffic_circles2.topojson -p color colored_traffic_circles.geojson</code>. Even this ran too slowly so I had to
reduce to streets with more than two traffic circles.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/seattle_traffic_circles.png"></p>

<p>Here the darker the color, the more traffic circles present on that
street. For me the most interesting feature is how many traffic circles
in a N-S
direction are right next to State Highway 99 or near I-5. Is this an
attempt to mitigate traffic of people trying to use surface streets
instead of arterials? Possibly, though difficult to determine.
Regardless, 1042 is an impressive amount of traffic circles for a
metropolitan area this large.</p>

<h2>Notes</h2>

<ul>
<li>The City dataset has dates on traffic circle installations with the
oldest traffic circle being 18TH AVE E AND E HARRISON ST installed on
1/5/1976</li>
<li>Full size version of this map available
<a href="http://zachstednick.com/seattle_traffic_circles.html">here</a></li>
<li>All code available <a href="https://github.com/stedy/blog-supplemental">here</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
