<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: python,r,airports | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/python-r-airports/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-04-14T11:30:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is the most remote airport from the city it serves in the United States?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2019/05/04/what-is-the-most-remote-airport-from-the-city-it-serves-in-the-united-states/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-04T20:51:52-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2019/05/04/what-is-the-most-remote-airport-from-the-city-it-serves-in-the-united-states</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, there was a question on
<a href="https://travel.stackexchange.com/questions/137558/what-is-the-most-remote-airport-from-the-center-of-the-city-it-supposedly-serves">travel.SE</a> about locating the airport furthest
from the city it is supposed to serve. There are some interesing answers
including the winner from Paris where the airport is approximately 147
km away from the Paris metro area. I started to wonder about this
question for different airports
within the US and I stumbled onto this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_airports_in_the_United_States">Wikipedia page</a>
which served as a good baseline for a quick analysis.</p>

<p>I used the <a href="https://cloud.google.com/maps-platform/places/">Google Maps location
API</a> to calculate
latitude and longitude
for the center
of the town or city and location of the airport. I then used the Google
Maps directions API to calculate the driving distance between the
airport and the center of the town it serves. This lead to some
interesting edge cases. For example, Peach Springs, Arizona is on this
list and the airport is about 113 miles away:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/peach_springs_drive.png"></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peach_Springs,_Arizona">Peach Springs</a> is a Census Designated Place and largely serves the
Hualapai tribe. Should it have been included on this list?</p>

<p>I also noticed on this Wikipedia page that there are many airports with
split locations (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seattle%E2%80%93Tacoma_International_Airport">Sea/Tac
Airport</a>
for example)
or a single airport serving multiple locations such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harrisburg_International_Airport">Harrisburg
International
Airport</a>
serving
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harrisburg,_Pennsylvania">Harrisburg</a>/<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middletown,_Dauphin_County,_Pennsylvania">Middletown,
PA</a>).
For these cases I just used
the first city mentioned for this analysis. The Wikipedia article also
lists
enplanements as recorded by the FAA in 2015 which provides a useful
metric for comparison. First I looked
at distance to airport versus number of passengers:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/airport_all.png"></p>

<p>Not too surprising to observe that many of the airports have very few
emboardings each year and are reasonably close to the center of town.</p>

<p>Then I looked at only airports that had over one million enplanements
which narrowed my list of airports down to 27:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/airport_1mil.png"></p>

<p>To me it is interesting to note that San Diego, Boston and to some
extent Dulles are all close to the city center with relatively few
emboardings as compared to this subset. Also, I grew up in Fort Collins,
CO and have many fond memories as a child of driving across the plains
with Denver International Airport seeming so, so far away.</p>

<p>As always, full code available on
<a href="https://github.com/stedy/blog-supplemental">GitHub</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
