<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: seattle,restaurants | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/seattle-restaurants/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-01T15:19:37-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summarizing the Seattle restaurant scene in 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/12/28/summarizing-the-seattle-restaurant-scene-in-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-28T12:50:02-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/12/28/summarizing-the-seattle-restaurant-scene-in-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Seattle is experiencing sustained economic growth which manifests
itself in a variety of ways, one of the most visible being changes in
the restaurant
industry. However, tracking the exact changes can be difficult due
to a variety of factors such the size of the city and the difficulty in
aggregating reliable data. There are several options for attempting to
track changes such as scraping data from a review site such as Yelp or
Zomato, systematically
checking the Food section of the local paper, or going straight to the city
records and attempt to
determine what restaurant permits are being issued over time.</p>

<p>For the purposes of this analysis, I decided to compare official city permit
records with the Food column from a local paper, specifically <a href="http://www.thestranger.com/">The
Stranger</a>.</p>

<p>Earlier this year, I started scraping the <a href="http://www.seattle.gov/licenses/find-a-business">City of Seattle Business
License
database</a> which
tracks both permit issuance and revocations. The City of Seattle site
classifies permits based on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_American_Industry_Classification_System">NAICS
codes</a>.
Because I am only interested in restaurant related permits, I focused on
the following five NAICS codes: Breweries, Drinking Places
(Alcoholic Beverages), Mobile Food Services, Limited-Service
Restaurants, and Full-Service Restaurants. I tracked changes in permits
by
week which when looked at for the entire year produces the following
figure:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/City_DB_NAICS_2015.png"></p>

<p>Clearly a good time to be in the food truck business. Also I am not sure
why so many Limited-Service Restaurants are closing and so many
Full-Service
Restaurants are opening. It could be simply that the restaurant decided
to expand its service or attempt to cater to a different clientele.
According to the official
<a href="http://www.census.gov/cgi-bin/sssd/naics/naicsrch?code=722511&amp;search=2012">definition</a>,
the NAICS code for Full-Service Restaurant
is that &ldquo;Providing food services to patrons who order and are served
while seated and pay after eating&rdquo;. For more details
on these changes, I have made an <a href="http://seattlerestaurantchanges.com">interactive
site</a> that allows you to further
investigate by neighborhood and restaurant type.</p>

<p>For comparison, I looked at every column I could
find by <a href="http://www.thestranger.com/authors/31833/angela-garbes">Angela
Garbes</a> who
seems to be the main restaurant reporter at The Stranger. I looked at
every restaurant opening and closing she mentioned in her
column. I then
<a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1HFS4H8E-4RiM47pQzbauLzjfKSoEzv3IZ6Xl2PbHmIg/edit?usp=sharing">classified</a>
all the restaurants she mentioned
based on the same NAICS code to generate a similar figure:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/Stranger_NAICS_2015.png"></p>

<p>Obviously, she has a lot less data and her column is focused on more of
the narrative of big name restaurants that
have opened and less likely to focus on something like a new Taco Time.
She focuses a lot on local food events such as popup restaurants as well
as restaurant personnel which is not something that shows up in the
official city
statistics. Regardless, our figures look very similar and both of the
datasets
show that Full-Service Restaurants have had sustained growth over the
entire year, which makes for great storytelling either with data or a
narrative and
benefits all of us with increased diversity of restaurant options.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
