<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: r,python,feather,nps | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/r-python-feather-nps/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-02T14:01:32-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A National Parks tour with feather]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/04/16/a-national-parks-tour-with-feather/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-16T12:35:08-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/04/16/a-national-parks-tour-with-feather</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year is the 100th Anniversary of the National Park system and the
National Park Service is kicking things off with <a href="https://www.nps.gov/findapark/national-park-week.htm">National Park
Week</a> where every
National Park will be open for free. With all the savings, my next
thought was what would be the best way to visit all of them in a single
trip?</p>

<p>To calculate this, I used a variant of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concorde_TSP_Solver">Concorde
algorithm</a> which is
an algorithm for solving the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traveling_salesman_problem">Traveling Salesman
Problem</a> or
what is the shortest route I can use to visit every National Park?</p>

<p>This also gave me an excellent opportunity to use
<a href="https://blog.rstudio.org/2016/03/29/feather/">Feather</a> a way of writing
dataframes to disk for interchanging between R and Python. I wanted to
use R largely due to Michael Hahsler&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/mhahsler/TSP">TSP
library</a> and I wanted to use python
because of the ease of use of the Google Maps API client. Finally, I
wanted to make a static map to show the route and I decided return to R
and use the <a href="https://github.com/dkahle/ggmap">ggmap library</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/NP_tour.png"></p>

<p>I realize there are many ways to call R from Python and vice versa but I
wanted to try feather. As a first attempt, I was
pretty impressed with feather&rsquo;s ease of use. I did not have too large of
a dataset so I was unable to comment on the speed but simple reading and
writing in R and Python is made to feel very simple. The one issue I did run into was
more of a user issue and that it was challenging to rapidly flip back and forth
between the two languages as I iterated this code. The 0-index of Python versus
the 1-index of R is all handled by feather which is nice not to have to think
about.</p>

<p>As a whole, I highly recommend checking out feather and as for me, well
its time to hit the road and start visiting some National Parks and
according to Google Maps I only have 14832.8 miles to go.</p>

<p>My code for this lives
<a href="https://github.com/stedy/blog-supplemental">here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
