<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: political | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/political/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-02T23:49:11-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Election 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/12/08/election-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-08T14:30:57-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/12/08/election-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has now been a month since the 2016 US Presidential election and I am
still stunned by the outcome but am ready to move on.</p>

<p>The major issues I focused on while voting at the Presidential level
were a better climate policy
and more equal treatment for minorities and other marginalized
populations. When I stop and think about why these were the major issues
for me, I realize that I am pretty fortunate. I have a great job,
generally feel safe, and am optimistic overall about the future and the
economy.</p>

<p>The biggest realization for me was that although I care deeply about
these issues on a national level, I need to be more involved at the
community level.</p>

<p>After thinking about it, there are three ways I want to get more
politically involved:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Increase the amount of money I donate to specific organizations on a
recurring basis.</p></li>
<li><p>Get more involved with organizations that focus on climate advocacy
and immigrant populations. I did do some volunteer work with
<a href="https://carbonwa.org">CarbonWA</a> and I want to get more involved with
them as well as with an organization that focuses on immigrants such as
<a href="http://www.rewa.org/">ReWA</a></p></li>
<li><p>Write more letters to elected officials about the issues I am most
passionate about. I have helped make a github
<a href="https://github.com/openseattle/seattle-boundaries">repo</a> of all the
boundaries of my hometown and I have never used this for any reason
other than looking up addresses. At least I know where to look to figure
out the various districts I live in.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Will these actions by me make a difference on the national level? Not
likely but hard to say. What they will do for sure is to make an impact
at the local level and will help me to improve the community around me.
If these issues are important
enough for me to write this post about, then it goes to show that they
are important enough for me to get more involved with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
