<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: r,running | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/r-running/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-04T13:11:43-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Offsetting beer by running]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/offsetting-beer-by-running/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-10T14:24:32-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/01/10/offsetting-beer-by-running</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year, among other personal data, I tracked every bar I went to and
every mile I
<a href="http://zachstednick.name/blog/2014/02/06/foursquare-without-a-smartphone/">ran</a>.
Naturally my first question is do I run enough to offset the amount of
beer I am drinking (at bars)?</p>

<p>First we define some units. According to this Runner&rsquo;s World
<a href="http://www.runnersworld.com/tools/calories-burned-calculator">calculator</a>, at 8:45 minute/mile for my
weight I am burning 145 calories. Google says the amount of calories in
a <a href="https://www.google.com/?gws_rd=ssl#q=calories+in+a+pint+of+beer">pint of
beer</a> is about 180. Since I usually average about two beers each time I go to a bar, that simplifies the calculations. Over the course of the year, how often was I above or below the residual? To answer this, I used R and finally got around to trying <a href="https://github.com/hadley/tidyr">tidyr</a> which is pretty slick.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/running_vs_beers.png"></p>

<p>I thougth a lot about how to determine the residual but eventually
settled on calories out - calories in because I felt this method made the best
visualization. As you can see around week 30, I started to run more and
did a better job at offsetting my beer consumption. Obviously this is an
overly simplistic view of my caloric expenditure but shows some of the
interesting insights that can be gained from personal data.</p>

<p>As always, all code and data is in this github
<a href="https://gist.github.com/stedy/9f2ffa58e25cc52dbe2e">gist</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
