<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: biking,seattle | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/biking-seattle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-08-28T11:55:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Pronto]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/02/09/thoughts-on-pronto/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-09T17:21:05-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/02/09/thoughts-on-pronto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.prontocycleshare.com/">Pronto bikeshare</a> is in serious
financial trouble and may not make it
until the end of <a href="http://www.seattlebikeblog.com/2016/02/04/pronto-needs-city-buyout-before-end-of-march-how-did-we-get-here/">March of this
year</a>.
There has been a lot of talk about the future of Pronto and funding but for now I
just wanted to mention a few of the things I like
about Pronto.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It is an excellent great for connecting mass transit and your final destination.
Waiting for a bus transfer and then taking said transfer sometimes
feels like it takes forever and
hopping on a Pronto bike can make the trip dramatically faster.</p></li>
<li><p>It provides an ideal solution for just going somewhere and not worrying about your bike.
Worried about locking up your bike in a certain area at a certain
time? If there is a Pronto station nearby that problem can be easily
fixed.</p></li>
<li><p>It is fun, full stop. The bikes are very sturdy and while they can feel
a bit slow I never feel like they will have physical problems or break
down. Yeah, I
realize I look like a dork while riding it but then again I run
my own blog, who am I to judge?</p></li>
<li><p>Finally, cars treat you as if you have never been on a bike before and
give you significant leeway. On my commuter bike I often get buzzed by
cars but on a Pronto I get treated like some tourist who has no
clue what they are doing. From a safety standopint, thats pretty tough
to beat.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I think that Pronto had a terrible rollout (starting a bikeshare program
in October?) and as multiple people have
shown, it does not have the best station placement compared to a
similarly sized metropolitan area.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en"
dir="ltr">Seattle&#39;s <a
href="https://twitter.com/CyclePronto">@CyclePronto</a> and DC&#39;s <a
href="https://twitter.com/bikeshare">@bikeshare</a> at the same scale.
Maybe hills &amp; helmets aren&#39;t the problem? <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SEABikes?src=hash">#SEABikes</a> <a
href="https://t.co/at9HjJkDxX">pic.twitter.com/at9HjJkDxX</a></p>&mdash;
Jake Vanderplas (@jakevdp) <a
href="https://twitter.com/jakevdp/status/695393881710419970">February 4,
2016</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"
charset="utf-8"></script>


<p> I have had multiple
problems with bike docks and the helmet locker can sometimes be unresponsive. But, even after all that, I
am long on Pronto and am constantly telling people about it. I had an
<a href="http://prontostories.com">entry</a> in the <a href="http://www.prontocycleshare.com/datachallenge">Pronto Data
Challenge</a>. I was even
planning on doing both the <a href="http://www.cascade.org/rides-major-rides/emerald-city-bike-ride">Emerald
City Bike
Ride</a>
and
<a href="http://obliteride.org/">Obliteride</a> on a Pronto bike just because I
thought it would be fun.</p>

<p>Seattle is growing,
really fast in fact, and giving people as many transit options as
possible will only make it that much easier for people to move around. I
really hope that Pronto lasts longer than the end of March and is
eventually able
to expand to cover more areas. As to whether the city should step in to
save it or not, we&rsquo;ll leave that
exercise to the reader.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
