<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript,imdb | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/javascript-imdb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-04-14T11:09:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pair Programming With a 13 Month Old]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2021/04/14/pair-programming-with-a-13-month-old/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-14T11:02:42-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2021/04/14/pair-programming-with-a-13-month-old</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming">Pair Programming</a> is a
software development method that uses two programmers on one
workstation thereby writing code as a team. I did a slight variation of this on a recent
project with a thirteen month old and had pretty good success.</p>

<p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/af/Pair_programming_1.jpg/1024px-Pair_programming_1.jpg" alt="Pair
Programming" /></p>

<p>I used to really like this site [GraphTV] and was sad when it closed. I later found <a href="http://www.omdbapi.com/">OMDb API</a> which I
 used to recreate GraphTV as a command line program on [GitHub]. But who wants to use a command line program to look
things up? I knew it could be much better hosted on its own website
which meant improving my JavaScript and a ideally use a JS charting
library (I ultimately went with <a href="https://www.chartjs.org/">Chart.js</a>). In a past life I wrote a lot of R code and JS often feels
incredibly foreign to me for reasons I cannot quite articulate.</p>

<p>These days I spend most of my time with a 13 month old and have pretty limited amounts of time
here and there for writing code. I do find that when working on a
programming problem that it can be incredibly easy for me
to run into a roadblock, hop on <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/tags/javascript">SO</a> and then find myself further out in the
weeds and really frustrated.</p>

<p>With this project, I took a different approach. Any time I ran into a roadblock I did a quick search on SO, read a few answers and then just closed my laptop and walked away. Granted this was not the fastest way to solve the problem but it did lead to many minor epiphanies in quotidian parenting events:
- Playing with some books on the floor and thinking &ldquo;The
<code>innerHTML</code>
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Element/innerHTML">element</a> is not flushing everything out, maybe there is a
dedicated function in Chartjs&rdquo;.
- Trying to get the 13 month old to eat more and thinking &ldquo;Why am I using this unwieldy CSV file when I could simplify my code so much
with a JSON object&rdquo;.
- Changing a diaper and thinking &ldquo;Well, I have tried everything else, did Bootstrap change something between v4.5 and <a href="https://blog.getbootstrap.com/2020/06/16/bootstrap-5-alpha/">5.0</a>&rdquo;?</p>

<p>I finally finished my project and launched
<a href="http://bingetrendy.com/">bingetrendy</a>!
I am not nor will ever be a shredding programmer and I am okay with
that. I also realize that not everyone might have their own 13 month old to help distract them.
However, I strongly feel that walking away from my code for extended periods of time
was beneficial for me and may be beneficial for you as well. Now if you
will excuse me, the 13 month old is asleep and I want to figure out what
episodes of <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0472954/episodes?season=6">It&rsquo;s Always Sunny in Philadelphia Season
6</a> I should
watch.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
