<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: running | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/running/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-02-04T15:21:21-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First year on Fitbit]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/02/25/first-year-on-fitbit/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T14:15:11-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2015/02/25/first-year-on-fitbit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a year on <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/user/2F49C2">Fitbit</a>, I figured it might be time to take a look at the data that I have been generating. Unfortunately, Fitbit makes you sign up for <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/premium/export">Premium</a> which charges you $50 per year to export your data. Fortunately, Cory Nissen has created an excellent <a href="https://github.com/corynissen/fitbitScraper">R package</a> for doing just this. The package simply uses a POST request handled by Hadley&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/hadley/httr">httr</a> library to generate a cookie and then parses the returned JSP results to return a nice <code>data.frame</code>.</p>

<p>Anyways, onto the data.</p>

<p>The first command I tried was the <code>get_15_min_data()</code> for parsing step
data in 15 minute increments. I figured that looking at yesterday&rsquo;s data
would be granular enough to get a good feel for the data.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/fifteen_min_fitbit.png"></p>

<p>I then plotted number of steps taken per day, with a smoothing function
overlaid:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/one_year_fitbit_steps.png"></p>

<p>I had a mean step count of 13935 for the past year. This data is more
interesting to look at as more of an overall trend. There definitely a
seasonal trend in the summer which makes sense. I can also see the
signatures of when I went on a four day backpacking trip in August and
when I broke two ribs and was confined to the couch for four days in
mid-March.</p>

<p>Since I have a Fitbit one, I can also measure floors climbed.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/fitbit_one_year_floors.png"></p>

<p>My mean number of floors climbed is 69.62 which seems absurdly high. My
desk is on the fourth floor of my building and I usually take the stairs
but not sure that is enough to fully explain why these counts are so
high.</p>

<p>Still, it is pretty interesting to look at this data outside of the
Fitbit interface and I would highly recommend checking out Cory&rsquo;s github
<a href="https://github.com/corynissen/fitbitScraper">repo</a></p>

<p>Also, speaking of github, for those of you who regularly follow this
blog (hi, Mom!) I have moved away from making a new gist every time to
simply having a standalone
<a href="https://github.com/stedy/blog-supplemental">repo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
