<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: r,twitter | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/r-twitter/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-04-14T11:27:39-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A forgotten cron job leads to interesting results]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/03/02/a-forgotten-cron-job-leads-to-interesting-results/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T15:15:33-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/03/02/a-forgotten-cron-job-leads-to-interesting-results</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On January 1, 2016 I set up a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">cron</a> job to perform a daily count of the number of Twitter followers of the two main Gubernatorial candidates in Washington State: <a href="https://twitter.com/GovInslee">Jay Inslee</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/BillBryantWA">Bill Bryant</a>. I was not attempting to predict the election or do anything with the data, I just wanted to count followers until Election Day 2016 and hopefully plot some interesting results. I checked on Election Day and the trend lines remained pretty much the same as they did at the start of the year so I abandonded my idea. Today I was cleaning out my crontab file and I found that the cron job was still running. I added a solid line for the 2016 Election Day and dashed line for the 2017 Presidential Inauguration.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/Inslee_vs_Bryant.png"></p>

<p>To me, the follower count data after the inauguration is the most interesting but it is just count data and I am not sure how much you can really read into it. If anything, forgetting the cron job was a pleasant surprise that reminded me of this guy who took a screenshot of the New York Times frontpage everyday for 5 years <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sCKGOiauJCE">YouTube</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
