<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: r,legislature,d3 | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/r-legislature-d3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-04-05T11:27:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visualizing the 2017-18 WA State Legislature]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2018/04/05/visualizing-the-2017-18-wa-state-legislature/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-05T11:25:23-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2018/04/05/visualizing-the-2017-18-wa-state-legislature</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In his <a href="https://www.governor.wa.gov/news-media/news-media/speeches/2018-state-state">2018 State of the State
speech</a>,
Washington State Governor Jay Inslee
made a passioned appeal for a carbon tax and proposed one in Washington
State Senate bill
<a href="http://apps2.leg.wa.gov/billsummary?BillNumber=6203&amp;Year=2017">6203</a>.
Because of this, I paid more attention to the
activities of the Washington State Legislature than I ever had before
and I found it fascinating.</p>

<p>First off, lets start with the website for the state Legislature. Here
is a screenshot of the
Washington State Legislature page for SB 6203 which is the bill I was
most interested in:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/WA_6203.png"></p>

<p>The website is very resource dense and well worth time exploring when
the Legislature is in session. Every piece of proposed legislation
shows the same amount of information and allows you to easily find and
contact your legislators about a particular bill if interested. The site
also has livestreams of <a href="http://apps2.leg.wa.gov/billsummary?BillNumber=6203&amp;Year=2017#videoSection">committee
hearings</a>
and displays <a href="https://app.leg.wa.gov/far/Senate/Calendar">vote
counts</a> on bills in almost
real time as the votes are tallied on both the
Senate and the House floor.</p>

<p>Is Washington state unique in this regard? Of course not, here is a
screen shot for an interesting bill in Legislature for the State of
California.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/CA_827.png"></p>

<p>Finally here is a screenshot of a House bill on the United States
Congress website</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/HR_5031.png"></p>

<p>Does ease of use of the website increase participation in the civic
process at the state level? That is a difficult question to answer but
personally I am glad I get to use the Washington State one instead of
the California state Legislature webpage.</p>

<p>The 2017-18 Washington State Legislative Session ended on <a href="http://leg.wa.gov/legislature/Documents/2018CutoffCalendar.pdf">March 8,
2018</a>
and
Governor Inslee then had 21 days to sign bills into law or veto them.</p>

<p>The conclusion of the 2017-18 Session made me wonder what happened to
those bills that were introduced and how many of them actually became
law.
In addition to a great website, the Washington State
Legislature also has an excellent set of <a href="http://wslwebservices.leg.wa.gov/">Web
Services</a> that allow for
programmatically
capturing metrics and data about activities in the state
legislation. One way to easily visualize this is with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sankey_diagram">Sankey
Diagram</a> (no relation to
this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6Iec080MWCs">Sankey</a> though).</p>

<p>Here is a smaller image of the diagram with a larger version [here]</p>

<iframe src="http://zachstednick.com/WA_leg_sankey.html" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" style="height:500px; width:1060px;" scrolling="no"></iframe>


<p>Code to generate this figure available on my <a href="https://github.com/stedy/blog-supplemental/">GitHub repo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
