<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: internet | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/internet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-09T21:38:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Standing up for net neutrality]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/07/05/standing-up-for-net-neutrality/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-05T21:26:12-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/07/05/standing-up-for-net-neutrality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Currently there are many political issues that demand
attention however in my opinion there are none that would affect more
people than the possible destruction of net neutrality.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Net_neutrality">Net neutrality</a> is simply the principle that all data on the internet
should be treated the same. It does not matter if you are visiting Fox
News or Mother Jones - the data and content from both of these
websites (as well as from every other website) should be treated as
equal and that data should be served equally by all Internet Service Providers. Losing net neutrality could
lead to an internet that favors
one of these two sites based on which site is willing to pay more. I
chose these sites because they are such polar opposites but at the same
time we live in a country that allows for such opposites to
have equal protection of freedom of speech. I may disagree with the content of a particular
website but
I do not think it should be served any differently than the website of a
site I do agree with. Destruction of net neutrality will lead to greater
influence wielded by larger corporations and could
stifle smaller websites and startups.</p>

<p>Fortunately, there is still time to act. On July 12, various online
communities and users will come together to stand tall and sound the
alarm about the FCC&rsquo;s attack on net neutrality. Join us
<a href="https://www.battleforthenet.com/july12">here</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
