<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pronto,biking,seattle,r | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/pronto-biking-seattle-r/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-12-03T22:13:24-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pronto post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/03/26/pronto-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-26T17:21:03-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/03/26/pronto-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pronto bike share ends this Friday March 31st and I will miss it for
sure. I <a href="http://zachstednick.name/blog/2016/02/09/thoughts-on-pronto/">wrote about why Pronto mattered to me</a> and I
even rode a Pronto bike in the 25
mile <a href="http://www.obliteride.org/">Obliteride</a> last year:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/IMG_2260.JPG"></p>

<p>In October 2015, there was a Pronto sponsored
<a href="https://www.prontocycleshare.com/datachallenge">contest</a> to visualize
bikeshare ride data. I created an
<a href="http://prontostories.com/">entry</a> which although did not win, was a
nice introduction for me to learn mapping with
<a href="d3js.org">D3</a>. As I was
checking out the Pronto site one last time today I noticed that they had
updated their publically available dataset to include 2016
ride data as well as the 2015 ride data.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/pronto_historical_ridership.png"></p>

<p>To me it seems that Pronto had a hard time expanding and encouraging
repeat riders. Unfortunately we do not have the membership data but if
we can assume that people who did not ride much in 2015 did not renew
their membership in 2016 then it looks pretty clear that Pronto was hurting
more than people thought. Also, it looked like they had good success in
2015 with getting people to buy day passes especially during peak tourist
season in the summer and were able to replicate that success in 2016. I
feel there is a need for a dedicated
bike share in Seattle however this iteration of bike share does not
appear to be the solution we need.</p>

<p>I went back to the Pronto site to fetch all my data because of an idea I
worked on then abandoned last summer. The idea was for a website that
was basically <a href="https://www.strava.com/">Strava</a> for Pronto
whereby you compared your ride time data to everyone else&rsquo;s and mapped out how
fast you were compared to them. Pronto did not make it easy to download
all your trip data so I ended up having to write a webscraper to get out
my own data (Hint, hint Pronto 2.0!) which I put at this <a href="https://github.com/stedy/pronto-scraper">GitHub
repository</a>. I never was able
to get my project past the personal level and my ultimate goal was to
simply make a map of the route and add
in plots. Here is an example of all trips from Fairview Ave N &amp; Ward St
to Westlake Ave &amp; 6th Ave:</p>

<iframe src="http://zachstednick.com/strava_for_pronto_demo.html" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" style="height:700px; width:1260px;" scrolling="no"></iframe>


<p>I&rsquo;m sad that I can&rsquo;t work on this project anymore but maybe with Pronto
2.0 I will be able to revist this idea.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
