<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-08-28T11:23:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The first book of the year is always a biography]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2020/01/02/the-first-book-of-the-year-is-always-a-biography/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-02T23:47:35-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2020/01/02/the-first-book-of-the-year-is-always-a-biography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few years I have tried to start each New Year off by
selecting a biography as the first book I read that particular year.
I have no specific methodology as to why I choose the biographies I do,
often
it is from something tangential to the topic of the biography or just
because I am interested in the topic in general. Here are some of my
recent picks
as well as my pick for 2020:</p>

<p><strong>2016 - <a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/15743242">Elon Musk: Tesla, SpaceX, and the Quest for a Fantastic
Future</a></strong></p>

<p>I picked up this one largely because I was interested in Elon Musk and
curious to learn more about him. This book was illuminating in regards
to how much self-confidence Musk has in himself and how much he was
willing to double down on himself and how frequently that was
all he needed to move on to more stable ground.</p>

<p><strong>2017 - <a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/8586497">Spread Spectrum</a></strong></p>

<p>I was interested in reading more about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedy_Lamarr">Hedy
Lamarr</a> and this book seemed
like a great place to start. It was self-published and quite bizarre at
times but it did explain technical details quite well and was well-paced
which more than made up for the author&rsquo;s unconventional asides.</p>

<p><strong>2018 - <a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/1653761">The Man Who Fed the World: Nobel Peace Prize Laureate Norman
Borlaug and His Battle to End World
Hunger</a></strong></p>

<p>I was
really interested in learning more about
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Borlaug">Borlaug</a> and his
contributions to agronomy but this particular biography was sloppy and
rife with colloquialisms. Borlaug was a fascinating character who likely
saved billions of people from starvation and demands a better biography
than this one.</p>

<p><strong>2019 - <a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/22229559">I Am Dynamite!: A Life of
Nietzsche</a></strong></p>

<p>I did not initially set out to read this book as my first book of the
year. Unfortunately, the book I had
planned on reading, <a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/18814688">In the Great Green Room: The Brilliant and Bold Life
of Margaret Wise</a>, was so
bad
that I bailed on it and read the Nietzsche biography instead. Prior to
reading, I was aware of
Nietzsche if only because of the famous &ldquo;God is dead&rdquo; quote and
something
vaguely related to Nazism. I was fascinated to learn more about him and
how
his writings were completely reappropriated after his death. This was
one of the better books I read all year.</p>

<p>Finally, in 2020 the first book I am reading is <strong><a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/14139984">Empress Dowager Cixi:
The Concubine Who Launched Modern
China</a></strong>. Each year I try
to alternate between male and female biographies and after bailing on
the biography of Margaret Wise last year, I felt it was time to read a
female biography to start 2020. I am also quite interested in China and while
I realize this book might be quite revisionist am curious to learn more
about Cixi and her role in developing modern day China.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First book of the year]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/01/01/first-book-of-the-year/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-01T15:10:38-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/01/01/first-book-of-the-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year I started off the year by making Ashlee Vance&rsquo;s
<a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/15743242/book/124695914">biography</a>
of Elon Musk the first book I read all year.
I wanted to start 2016 off better than 2015 and thought this book might
help my thinking. The story is on Musk is quite interesting if anything
to simply show how much he believes in himself even when the odds seem
stacked against him and the money in the bank grows lower. I tried to
use Musk&rsquo;s story to improve my own self-confidence and I felt like the most concrete way I
was able to do so was to reduce the amount I took on and instead focus
on doing a better job of what I had in front of me.</p>

<p>I will be repeating this little project in 2017 by starting the year off
by reading <a href="https://www.librarything.com/work/8586497">Spread Spectrum:Hedy Lamarr and
the mobile phone</a> by Rob
Walters. I know very little about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spread_spectrum">spread spectrum
technology</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedy_Lamarr">Hedy
Lamarr</a> had a very
interesting life and is greatly underappreciated in
modern society. Hopefully this book will prove to be as motivational
over the course of the year in a similar manner as Musk&rsquo;s biography was.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
