<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: r,football | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/r-football/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-30T13:12:35-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Has the Pac-12 Network decreased UW home football game attendance UPDATED]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/11/30/has-the-pac-12-network-decreased-uw-home-football-game-attendance-updated/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-30T13:10:16-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/11/30/has-the-pac-12-network-decreased-uw-home-football-game-attendance-updated</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following up on my earlier
<a href="http://zachstednick.name/blog/2016/09/02/has-the-pac-12-network-decreased-uw-home-football-game-attendance/">post</a>,
how much has the Pac-12 Network affected game attendance? I updated my previous data set to include the past two seasons so as to include 2008-2017 data. I relied on home game
attendance as reported by Wikipedia and also used Wikipedia to determine what TV network broadcast each home game. In an ideal world I would be able to make better comparisons using the <a href="http://www.nielsen.com/us/en/solutions/measurement/television.html">Nielsen rating</a>
for each game however my guess is that data does not come as cheap or as
easily as data from Wikipedia. For the purposes of this analysis I am
neglecting various other factors in this anaysis
such as time at kickoff, game day temperature, opponent, ranking of UW,
ranking of opponent, etc&hellip; the list goes on and on. My main intention
was
to simply show home game attendance versus TV network for all games:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/UW_football_attendance_by_TV_2008-17.png"></p>

<p>And attendance for Pac-12 only opponents versus TV network:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/UW_football_attendance_by_TV_2008-17_Pac12_only.png"></p>

<p>Based on the available data it appears that attendance during home games
has
been influenced and possibly decreased by the Pac-12 Network but it is
difficult to say for sure while ignoring so many external factors. With
a significant budget deficit still a major
<a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/education/uw-regents-assail-ex-athletic-director-over-growing-deficit/">issue</a>,
one can only hope that losses from game day ticket sales are made up for
with Pac-12 Network advertising revenue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Has the Pac-12 Network decreased UW home football game attendance?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/09/02/has-the-pac-12-network-decreased-uw-home-football-game-attendance/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-02T12:52:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2016/09/02/has-the-pac-12-network-decreased-uw-home-football-game-attendance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The University of Washington Husky football team is taking on Rutgers
this Saturday with kickoff at 11 AM PST. This is awfully early to start a game, especially a game that occurs during Labor Day weekend. The game is being aired on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pac-12_Network">Pac-12 Network</a> which is about to enter its fifth year of operation. This made me wonder, with the presence of the Pac-12 Network, has attendance decreased at home UW football games?</p>

<p>Fortunately, Wikipedia lists game attendance which allows for a quick
overview of UW home games stratified by network:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/UW_football_attendance_by_TV.png"></p>

<p>The purple dots are UW home games shown on the Pac-12 network, not
entirely convincing but at first glance they don&rsquo;t look too great for
the network. I then looked at only home Pac-10/Pac-12 games and looked at attendance
by season:</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/UW_football_total_attendance.png"></p>

<p>That high point in this figure is UW versus Oregon in 2013 while that particularly low point in 2015 was versus Arizona on Halloween
which happened to fall on a Thursday in 2015. Why some executive at FS1 thought it would be a good idea to schedule a game then is beyond me.</p>

<p>In 2012, UW played its home games at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CenturyLink_Field">CenturyLink
Field</a>, while <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Husky_Stadium">Husky
Stadium</a> was renovated. For the 2013 season the UW football team returned to play at a smaller Husky
Stadium, did either of these factors impact attendance?</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/UW_football_percentage_capacity.png"></p>

<p>Not really, there is a minimal difference in stadium size which is
reflected in this identical-looking figure.</p>

<p>What Pac-12 opponents were the biggest draws on average?</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Opponent </th>
<th style="text-align:right;"> Average Attendance </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>          Oregon </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 69584</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Washington State </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 68862</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>        Colorado </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 64373</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>             USC </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 64046</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>    Oregon State </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 63777</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>        Stanford </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 63360</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>            UCLA </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 62544</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>      California </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 62541</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>         Arizona </td>
<td style="text-align:right;"> 60756</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Obviously there are a lot of factors that can&rsquo;t be captured by game
attendance alone but with a significant budget deficit largely blamed on
<a href="http://www.seattletimes.com/sports/uw-huskies/uw-athletic-department-projects-budget-deficit-of-14-million-for-2016-fiscal-year/">reduced
attendance</a>, it seems like it might be time for the UW to analyze if the Pac-12 Network has really been worth the investments to date.</p>

<p>Full code for scraping Wikipedia on
<a href="https://github.com/stedy/blog-supplemental">GitHub</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
