<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: r,basketball | Zach Stednick]]></title>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/categories/r-basketball/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stedy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-09-20T00:04:12-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stedy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Stednick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Have there been more upsets in the NCAA Tournament recently?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/03/07/have-there-been-more-upsets-in-the-ncaa-tournament-recently/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-07T13:19:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stedy.github.io/blog/2017/03/07/have-there-been-more-upsets-in-the-ncaa-tournament-recently</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been following the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCAA_Division_I_Men%27s_Basketball_Tournament">NCAA Men&rsquo;s Basketball
Tournament</a>
for as long
as I can remember and with Selection Sunday coming up, I wondered if
there
have been more or less upsets in recent tournaments. To look at this
visually I used a hypothetical perfect bracket as a reference (i.e. #1
seed beats #16 seed, #2 seed beats #15 seed all the way to #1 seed beating a #2 seed). I
took the sum of all the winning seed numbers at each round in the
Regional Tournament and used that as the denominator
for comparison with the other Regional Tournaments for that particular
year.</p>

<p>I went back in time as far as I could but the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2007_NCAA_Division_I_Men's_Basketball_Tournament">2007
Tournament</a>
finally harmonized the names of the Regional tournaments with the names
East, West, South, and
Midwest which made for easier comparison across years.</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/NCAA_by_region.png"></p>

<p>Clearly there have been quite a lot of upsets in the past ten years
especially within the Midwest Region.</p>

<p>I then went back and looked at all games back to 1985 when
the Tournament first expanded to 64 teams. For this I did not have all
the Regional Tournament information so I just looked at all the games
(except the Final Four).</p>

<p><img src="http://zachstednick.com/NCAA_all_by_year.png"></p>

<p>The aggregate data is pretty volatile year over year as well with a low
in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2007_NCAA_Division_I_Men's_Basketball_Tournament">2007</a>. If anything, this shows we should be in for another great year of NCAA tournament basketball complete with some (hopefully many) exciting upsets.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
